（重役１）タンデムミラー
エンジン２号機の―
Damage resulting from the meltdown of the #2
tandem mirror engine has reached 800 billion.
メルトダウンによる
損害は―
８,０００億に
上っています
（重役２）我が社の
イメージ悪化も深刻です
There has also been a serious worsening
of the company's public image.
Technora is the key figure in the construction
of the Von Braun, after all.
テクノーラ社が中心に
なっていますからね
（重役３）次に
大きな事故が起これば―
If there is another serious accident, we'll be
looking not only at a setback for the project,
計画の頓挫は もちろん―
莫大な金銭補償と
世間の悪評を負うことになります
...but also massive financial settlement
payments and a public scandal.
Which is one of the reasons why
we must put some distance...
そのためにも
木星開発計画と我が社は―
...between our company and the
Jupiter development project.
距離を置く必要がある
We need a warning bell,
as well.
（重役２）鈴も必要ですし
（会長）それで この会社ですか
And that is why you've
created this company.
Galileo Development. We're working through
three levels of intermediary companies,
（重役４）ガリレオ開発―
３つの会社を
経由していますので―
法的には 完全に別会社です
...so legally speaking, it is a completely
independent entity.
I'm sending Dolf Azaria, the current Second
Division Director that I mentioned the other day,
（専務）
新会社には代表取締役として―
先日 お話しした 第２事業部部長
ドルフ･アザリアを出向させます
...to act as representative director
of the new company.
うーん 空席となったポストは？
What about the post
he'll be vacating?
（ノーマン）
本日より 第２事業部を―
I'm Norman Schwimmer, and I've been put in
charge of Second Division starting today.
任されることになった
ノーマン･シュワイマーだ
On the insistence of Chairman Joshua,
I will be serving concurrently...
ヨシュア会長から
是非にとのお声がかりで―
第３事業部部長と
兼務することになった
...as director of both Second
and Third Divisions.
アハハ
兼務とはいえ 今日から私が―
Now, while this may be an additional post
for me, it doesn't change the fact...
第２事業部の
トップであることに変わりはない
...that I am the top dog in
Second Division starting today.
I'm going to be running things
my own way from now on.
これからは
私のやり方でやらせてもらう
いいな
Is that clear?
I suggest that you forget everything about
how the old director ran the division.
前の事業部長のやり方は
全て忘れるように
♪～
Soshite hito wa toki wo koeta yume wo miru
And people dream dreams that transcend time.
♪そして人は時空(とき)を
越えた夢を見る
seijyaku no umi ni idakarete
Held in the depths of the sea.
♪静寂の宇宙(うみ)に抱かれて
tori ya kumo wo miagete wa
As they look up at the stars and clouds.
♪鳥や雲を見上げては
hakanai inochi moyashita ikusen no asa ni
It set their ephemeral souls on fire on a thousand mornings.
♪儚(はかな)い生命(いのち)燃やした
♪幾千の朝に
hikari ga mukau basho he habataku darou
I bet they're taking right to where the light is headed.
♪光が向かう場所へ
♪羽ばたくだろう
daichi wo ima tori yoku kette
Now kickoff from the ground like a bird.
♪願いを放つ時は今
hatenaki yume wo noseta furontia he
Off into the frontier that is carrying boundless dreams.
♪果てなき夢を乗せた
♪フロンティアへ
tooku tooku dive in the sky
Farther and farther dive in the sky.
♪遠く遠く Dive in the Sky
（タナベ）
えっ デブリ課が解散？
Debris Section's
gonna be disbanded?!
（ラビィ）えっ
（課長）さっき―
I was just told in person
by Director Norman.
Phase 18
Debris Section's Last Day
ノーマン新事業部長から
直接 言われた
He said we'll be disbanded
at the end of the week.
今週末で解散だって
企業としての体裁より
収益が大事とかで
Something about earnings being more
important to a company than its image.
（ラビィ）そんな
He can't! What's gonna
happen to us?
（ラビィ）
じゃ 我々はどうなるんです？
異動ですか？ それとも…
Will we be transferred? Or...
Fired.
（エーデル）クビ
（タナベ）まさか
They wouldn't!
（課長）いや そうかも
リストラとか言ってたし
No, she might be right.
He mentioned something about downsizing.
（ラビィ）うっそー
（課長）本当
You're kidding!
It's true!
（フィー）あのじじい
That old bastard still has it in for us
over what happened with that test module.
実験モジュールの件
まだ根に持ってやがるな
（ラビィ）だから
あのとき 私は反対したんだ
That's why I was against getting involved!
Look what you've done!
どうしてくれるんだよ！
家族だって
養わなくちゃいけないのに
I still have a family
to provide for!
Um... I thought you and
your wife had split up.
（タナベ）あの…
奥さんとは別れたんじゃ？
Maybe, but I had seven
children with her!
でも 女房との間には
７人の子供がいるの！
つまり 養育費も７倍
That means child support
times seven!
そりゃあさ
うちはぶっちぎりで赤字だし―
But we're always running deep in the red, and
we don't have any connections at the top!
上にもコネないけどさ
Quit your damn crying!
（フィー）泣くな！ うっとうしい
まだ クビとは限らないだろ
Nobody said we're
gonna be fired!
（ラビィ）そうだ 接待だ
She's right!
Let's wine and dine them!
みんなで接待して
なんとかして許してもらうんだ
We'll all entertain them to smooth things over
and try to get him to forgive us!
なっ？
Right?
私は派遣ですから
I'm only a
temp worker.
あ…
（タナベ）先輩 大変です
デブリ課が解散しちゃうって
Senpai! This is terrible!
They say Debris Section
is gonna be disbanded!
（ハチマキ）ああ 聞こえてたよ
Yeah, I heard you
in there.
No matter how precious their profits are to
them, don't you think this is going too far?
いくら収益が大事だからって
あんまりだと思いません？
（ハチマキ）ああ そうだな
Yeah, I guess.
If we don't come up with a way to keep
them from disbanding us, we're gonna...
（タナベ）解散させないように
私たちも何かしないと
（操作音）
（ハチマキ）そうだな
Yeah, I guess...
（ハチマキ）
とりあえず 飯食いに行くわ
Let's get something to eat. I'm starving.
腹 減った
は？
Huh?
Aren't you supposed
to be working today?
（ハキム）
今日は 仕事じゃなかったのか？
営業軌道の資料を整理をするとか
Sorting management orbit
paperwork or some such?
（クレア）サボり
（ハキム）え？
I'm playing hooky.
It's all right.
（クレア）いいの
どうせ仕事は 全部 外されちゃって
やることないから
Anyway, I've been taken off all my duties,
so I don't have anything to do.
（ハキム）どうして？
Why's that?
最近 失敗続きだったし―
I've had one failure
after another lately.
前の事業部長派って
思われてるみたい
Plus, I guess they think I'm a member
of the old division director's clique.
（ハキム）派閥争いか
Political infighting, huh?
なんか ばかばかしくなっちゃった
It all seems so stupid
to me now.
地球に降りて結婚でもしよっかな
Maybe I'll go down to Earth and
get married or something.
嫌だ 黙らないでよ 冗談…
Come on, don't go silent on me. I was joking.
- Claire.
（ハキム）クレア
（クレア）え？
（ハキム）
マナンガって国を知ってるかい？
Do you know a country
named Mananga?
中東の産油国ね
An oil-producing country
in the Middle East, right?
石油が使われなくなってからは
内乱続きって聞いたけど
I'd heard that there's been constant civil wars
there ever since oil stopped being used.
（ハキム）僕のふるさとだ
（クレア）え？
It's my homeland.
（ハキム）
貧困が内乱を呼び 政府は分裂状態
Poverty triggered the civil wars, and
the government is in a state of chaos.
連合の手を借りないと
選挙も満足にできない
We can't even hold fair elections
without going to INTO for help.
それが僕の祖国なんだ
That's what my homeland
is like.
You're taking personal command
out here today, ma'am?
（社員）今日は あねさん自ら
外で陣頭指揮ですか？
（フィー）
ああ これで最後らしいから
Yeah, 'cause it looks like this
is gonna be the last time.
まっ 船乗りの流儀ってやつでね
It's sort of a tradition
among sailors.
ユーリ そっちはどう？
Yuri, how's it look
on your end?
Fine. All green.
（ユーリ）ああ 問題ない
（フィー）何？
What?
Are you okay with this
being the last?
（ユーリ）いいのか？ 最後で
There's not much we can do.
It's the boss' decision.
（フィー）
しかたないでしょ 上の決定だもの
それに―
Besides, I can keep collecting debris
even if I'm not at Technora.
デブリは
テクノーラにいなくても拾えるさ
You're going to
change companies?
移るのか？ 会社
（フィー）さあ
I don't know... It wouldn't be the
first time I've switched companies,
（フィー）会社を変わるのは
初めてのことじゃないし―
...and there's also
what they did to Dolf.
ドルフのこともあるしね
Hey! Hey! Hey! Hey! I'm Lavie!
（ラビィ）はいはい はいはい
ラビィちゃんだよ
That was terrific! I haven't laughed
this hard in a long time!
（ノーマン）
いやー 傑作だ ハハハッ…
こんなに笑ったのは久しぶりだよ
いいだろう 君には
総務課の席を用意してやろう
All right, I'll find you a position in
General Affairs, how's that sound?
（ラビィ）
ははっ ありがとうございます
Thank you so much!
（ノーマン）たまには こういう
くだらないのもいいもんだ
It does a man good to enjoy nonsense
like this every once in a while.
An astute observation, Director Norman!
さすがはノーマン部長
The last director wasn't able to
enjoy this kind of entertainment.
前の事業部長は―
こういう楽しみ方の
できない方でしたから
Dolf has no idea how to use his human resources, keeping a man like you down in Half Section like that.
君のような人材を
半課に置いておくなんて―
ドルフは人の使い方を知らんな
今度の連合の接待も
よろしく頼むよ
I want you to handle the entertainment
the next time INTO visits.
うまくいったら係長を約束しよう
If it works out,
there's a manager position in it for you.
Really? Not assistant manager?
えっ？ 補佐が取れるんですか？
I look forward to seeing you
crack us all up.
爆笑ものの芸 期待してるよ
Thank you so much, sir! Thank you!
ありがとうございます
頑張ります
I'll give it
all I've got!
（タナベ）何やってんですか！
What the heck are
you doing?!
あっ…
This is no time to be reading
an EVA textbook!
（タナベ）今更 ＥＶＡ教本なんて
読んでる場合じゃないでしょう？
Our team is about
to be split up!
私たち
バラバラになっちゃうんですよ
You always said that space needed the Debris Section!
デブリ屋は
宇宙に必要だって言った…
（ハチマキ）おい 返せよ！
- Hey, give that back!
はい
Fine.
３年ぶりに読んだけど
結構 勉強になるな これ
I haven't read this thing in three years.
It's got some useful info in it.
（タナベ）
デブリ課が解散したら―
If Debris Section gets disbanded, making EVAs
is gonna be the least of our worries, you know?
ＥＶＡどころじゃ
ないじゃないですか
This isn't the only place
we can do EVA work.
（ハチマキ）ＥＶＡは
ここじゃなくてもできるだろ？
What about
debris retrieval?
デブリの回収は？
Yeah, that's nice...
ああ そうだな
C'mon, Senpai...
ねえ 先輩
もう いいです
Fine! Suit yourself!
I'll save Debris Section
all by myself if I have to!
私は１人でも
デブリ課を守りますから！
（ハチマキ）あっ…
No, honest! It's the truth!
（ラビィ）本当だ 本当なんだって
Daddy's gonna be made
into a manager!
お父さん 今度 係長になるんだぞ
（子供１）ちゃー
（子供２）すごーい
Are you gonna
get paid more?
（子供３）お給料も上がるの？
You bet, you bet!
上がる 上がる
Honest? Then buy me
a game!
ほんとに！ じゃ ゲーム買って
（子供４）サッカーボール
A wanna
soccer ball!
（子供１）ちゃー ちゃっちゃー
（子供５）私 望遠鏡
I want a telescope!
望遠鏡は高いよ
ゲームなら みんなで遊べるのに
Telescopes are expensive!
If Dad buys a game, we all can play with it!
No, that's okay! It's to celebrate
Daddy moving up in the world.
いいよ いいよ
お父さんが出世するお祝いだ
みんな買ってやるよ
I'll buy everything
you want!
（子供たちの歓声）
（子供２）
ねえ お父さん 出世したら―
If you've got a bigger job, Daddy, that means
you're gonna pick up bigger de-breeze, right?
もっといっぱい
デボを拾うんだよね？
（子供３）バーカ デブリだよ
Dummy, it's pronounced "de-bree"!
総務課の係長だからな
I'll be manager of General Affairs Section,
so I won't have to pick up debris anymore.
もう デブリを
拾わなくてもいいんだ
（子供たち）え？
じゃあ 誰が宇宙を守るの？
Then who's gonna
keep space safe?
え？
They're blowing things
out of proportion.
（ギガルト）
大げさにしよって
I'm not sick enough to be
put into the hospital yet.
（ギガルト）
まだ入院するほどじゃあない
通常勤務なら…
I can still
handle everyday...
Absolutely not.
駄目です
体調が万全でない者は―
Someone who isn't at 100% might put
the team as a whole in danger.
チーム全体を
危機に陥れる可能性があります
フッ フフフッ
俺が教えたんだったな
I taught you that,
didn't I?
コンディションを保つのも
仕事のうちだって
Maintaining your physical
condition is part of the job.
（ハキム）すいません 生意気を
I'm sorry if I spoke
out of turn, sir.
いや 俺は いい教え子を持ったな
Forget it.
I was lucky to have
such a good pupil.
（ハキム）先生
Sensei...
何だ？
Yeah?
I'm... quitting the Orbital Security Agency.
私は 軌道保安庁を…
I see... You're serious about this?
そうか 本気なんだな
（ハキム）はい
Yes, sir.
（タナベ）だから―
Like I said, my rank in the company
doesn't have anything to do with it!
平も部長も関係ないって
言ってるじゃないですか
（ゲイハート）
苦情なら 総務課人事に行きなさい
If you have a complaint, take it to General Affairs or Personnel!
（ゲイハート）
苦情なら 総務課人事に行きなさい
（タナベ）
１人の人間として…
- It's as a fellow human...
直接 事業部長に言いたいんです
But I want to tell the division director
in person!
In person? Who do you think you are,
you Half Section scum?
（ゲイハート）
直接とは何だ この半課者
まったく ばかばかしい
I swear, what a bunch
of nonsense...
（タナベ）あっ ちょっと！
Hey, wait!
（社員）しつこいな 君も
Give it a rest,
would you?!
くっ…
（クレア）無理よ
It's useless.
And what's that
supposed to mean?
どういう意味ですか？ それ
For someone at the bottom to defeat someone
at the top, regular tactics won't work.
（クレア）
下が上に勝とうと思ったら―
正攻法じゃ 駄目ってこと
は？
こ… これくらいかな？ どう？
Is this about right? How's it look?
A little more to the right, Assistant Chief.
（エーデル）
課長補佐 もうちょっと右です
（課長）あっ こ… こう？
あ あ あーっ…
How about now?
Are you all right?
（エーデル）大丈夫ですか？
（課長）いてててて…
課長補佐
Assistant Chief?
I'm sorry!
（課長）ごめんね…
ごめんね 何もできなくて
I'm sorry that I'm so useless!
デブリ課も守れないし―
I can't protect Debris Section, and I rely
on you to do everything for me, E-chan...
エーちゃんにも
お世話になりっぱなしだし
Even if I tried my hardest, it's probably
too late for me to make any difference...
駄目なんだろうね
今更 一生懸命にやろうとしても
Assistant Chief.
課長補佐
どうしよう みんなの老後
What's everybody gonna
do in their old age?
ん…
（ハチマキ）珍しいな
（タナベ）あ…
Now this is
a rare sight.
I didn't expect you to
come along, Lavie.
ラビィが
わざわざ ついてくるなんて
あっ ああ
最後のミッションだから
Mark confirmed. Zulu 1024, 36, 54.
Yes, well, it's our
final mission.
役職上さ
It's part of
my duties.
Guide us in until we reach orbit
correction point. You copy?
（ハチマキ）ふーん
I copy.
Datalink via area Navstars confirmed through Molniya orbit.
なあ ハチマキ
Say, Hachimaki...
俺たちってサラリーマンだよな
We really are corporate drones, aren't we?
（ハチマキ）何を今更
What brought
this on?
（ハチマキ）何を今更
（電子音）
Power transfer laser
tracking control is nominal.
（電子音）
（ユーリ）あっ 救難信号？
A distress signal?
Pass me the coordinates
of their location.
位置座標をこっちに回して
係長 仕事変更するけど いいよね？
Manager, I'm going to switch jobs.
That okay with you?
Sure...
ああ
最後のミッションは
漂流した宇宙船拾いか
So, our last mission will be rescuing
a spaceship that's adrift, huh?
宇宙を守るヒーローには
ピッタリだ
That's a perfect ending for
heroes who keep space safe.
Wow, that really
takes me back!
うわっ 懐かしいな
私がライセンスを取ったころの
作業船だよ
We were on a work boat like that
back when I got my license!
…てことは 20年以上の老朽船か
In other words, it's a rust bucket
that's over 20 years old, huh?
（フィー）これから接舷する
Now docking. Hachimaki, you stand by
in the Fishbone as planned.
ハチマキは予定どおり
フィッシュボーンで待機して
（ハチマキ）アイ コピー
I copy.
（フィー）ユーリとタナベは
酸素ボンベの準備
Yuri and Tanabe, get some
oxygen tanks ready.
Once I've docked, get confirmation of their
shipboard status. Especially the pressure.
ドッキングしたら
相手側の船内状況の確認をして
特に気圧
I copy.
（ユーリ）アイ コピー
（ユーリ）ハッチを開ける
Opening hatch.
ユーリさん
Yuri-san...
ああ 今 確認している
Yes. I am checking
it out right now.
Fee, target ship's pressure and
air circulation are both green.
フィー 対象の船内気圧 空気循環
共に問題なし
航行システムのみが
ダウンしている模様だ
It looks like it is only their
flight system that is down.
航行システムのみが
ダウンしている模様だ
（パイロット）だから
言ったじゃないですか
Didn't I tell you this
would happen?!
（パイロット）だから
言ったじゃないですか
これから船内状況の…
Will now check out
ship's interior.
これから船内状況の…
予定地を変えて―
I said that changing course and coming all the
way up into a Molniya orbit was a bad idea!
うん？ 生存者？
モルニア軌道まで来るのは
マズいって
Survivors?
I'm charging you for breach of contract
and repairs!
（パイロット）
違約金や修理代 頼みますよ
こっちは…
（監督）何言ってんだ
I'm just a courier!
- What're you talking about?
（監督）俺がシステムダウン
させたわけじゃないだろ？
I wasn't
the one who crashed your systems!
（監督）俺がシステムダウン
させたわけじゃないだろ？
（ＡＤ）監督 あまり
怒らせるとマズいっすよ
- Director, don't get too
worked up.
（ＡＤ）監督 あまり
怒らせるとマズいっすよ
大体 こんなボロボロで
誰が許すなんて言った
Besides, who told you to get us
a clunker like this?!
あーっ！ 無許可の監督
The unlicensed director!
ん？ 誰だ？ お前
Who are you?
It's me! We met on
the Luna Ferry!
（タナベ）
ほら ルナフェリーで会った
（監督）
ああ 頭が幸せなねえちゃんか
Oh, that girl who had
her head in the clouds!
何だ こいつらか
Oh, it's those guys.
You really saved
our skins!
Are you filming a movie
without a permit again?
知ってる人？
You know them?
ちょっとね
Something like that.
Hey, stop talking nonsense! Me and
my crew are social activists now!
つまんない出会いでさ… おっ？
We bumped into them when... Huh?
（ハチマキ）
おーい 俺 戻っていいかな？
Hey!
Can I come back in now? There wasn't any serious trouble, right?
問題は特になかったんだろう？
（フィー）待って ハチ
（ハチマキ）あ？
Hang on, Hachi.
（フィー）相対速度が
ほとんどゼロのデブリがある
There's some debris out there with
a relative velocity of about zero.
We can't look this gift horse in the mouth,
now can we?
こんな偶然
見過ごす手はないと思わない？
Anyway, it's our last job.
どうせ最後の仕事なんだしさ
Sure, why not?
まあ いいけど
（パイロット）すいません 会社に
連絡 入れとかないとマズいんで
I'm sorry, but I should really
check in with my company.
いいですよ
Sure, go ahead. Use the comm system
in our residential block.
居住区の通信システムを
使ってください
（パイロット）すいません どうも
Thanks, I appreciate it.
（監督）おっ
（ＡＤ）修理代 まけてくださいね
Cut us a deal on the
repair costs, okay?
（パイロット）知るか
The hell I will!
Anyway, I sold that movie I shot
on the Luna Ferry for a bundle,
（監督）…で ルナフェリーでの
ムービーが高く売れてさ
報道に転身 図ったわけ
...so I tried to get
into journalism.
なんだ
やっぱり お金儲けじゃないですか
I knew it, you're still in it
for the money, aren't you?
（監督）何言ってんだ
What're you talking about?
I'll suddenly be happy if I'm poor?
貧乏なら
不幸が幸福に変わるってのかよ
I'm just saying that your
motives are corrupt!
だから 動機が不純だと…
（フィー）駄目って どうして？
- We can't grab it? Why not?!
は？
（管制官）ですから―
We're saying that we don't want you to retrieve
the debris that you contacted us about!
連絡のあった対象デブリは
回収しないでいただきたい
（フィー）
他の会社の回収予定に入ってるの？
Is it on some other company's
retrieval checklist?
I say again, DS-12 is not to attempt retrieval,
and is to return to base at once.
（管制官）
繰り返します DS-12は―
対象デブリに触れず
直ちに帰投してください
ユー コピー？
You copy?
はあ？ だから理由を…
Huh? At least give me
a reason!
はあ？ だから理由を…
（通信の切れた音）
切っちゃったよ おい
何だ？ 今度の担当管制官
The jerk hung up
on me.
What's with this new Control supervisor
they gave us?
（ＡＤ）ほらほら 監督
やっぱ 機雷っすよ
See? I knew it, Director! It's gotta be a mine!
A mine?
機雷！？
There have been rumors that INTO has been
laying mines disguised as debris up here.
連合はデブリに見せかけて―
機雷を浮かべてるって
うわさがあってね
We came up here to expose
what they're doing.
俺たちはそいつを暴くために
来たってわけだ
じゃあ あれ 爆弾なんですか？
Is it some kind
of bomb, then?
Not exactly. They call it
a "data mine."
ちょっと違う
あれはデータ機雷とかいってな
When a ship comes close,
it burns out its flight systems.
近づいた船の航行システムを
焼いちまうんだ
（ユーリ）
じゃあ あなたたちの作業船が―
Oh, so that is what crashed
your work ship's systems.
システムダウンしたのは…
（監督）ああ あれは名目上
デブリってなってるだけさ
Yeah. It's listed as debris,
but it's anything but.
I can't believe dangerous things
like that are floating in space!
そんな危ないものが
宇宙に浮かんでるなんて
当然 放っておけないよな
Needless to say, we can't leave
that thing out there.
フィー君 まさか
Fee-kun, you aren't seriously
going to...
ここは ロシアやＥＵの
緊急避難用軌道でもあるし
Besides, this is an emergency evacuation
orbit used by Russia and the EU.
（ラビィ）ちょっと…
Hey!
If INTO is claiming it's just debris, then they
can't complain if we go pick it up, right?
（フィー）連合が
デブリって言い張るのなら―
私たちが回収しても
文句 言えないだろ
（タナベ）そうですよね
Yeah, right!
（ラビィ）待てよ
管制課が駄目って言ってるんだ
Wait! If Control Section says we can't,
then as loyal employees, we have to...
サラリーマンなら…
人命が懸かっているんですよ！
Lives are
at stake here!
あ…
It probably works by detecting changes
in the communications data environment.
（ユーリ）恐らく―
通信情報環境の変化を
認識するタイプだな
So it would react to
our Fishbones, too?
（フィー）じゃあ
フィッシュボーンでも―
反応するってこと？
One person will have to go solo in a spacesuit
with its face-computer shut off.
（ユーリ）フェイスコムを
カットした宇宙服―
身ひとつで行くしかない
But we don't have a lifeline
that'll reach that far!
（タナベ）でも あそこまで届く
命綱なんてないですよ
（ラビィ）
無理だよ 誰もできっこないって
It's hopeless! I'm telling you,
nobody could possibly do that!
I'll go.
（ハチマキ）俺が行く
Senpai?
先輩？
Weren't you listening, Hachimaki?
聞いてなかったのか？ ハチマキ
This is an S-class EVA
we're talking about!
こいつは
ＳクラスのＥＶＡなんだぞ
（ハチマキ）だから行くんだ
That's why I'm going.
これくらいできなきゃ
I have to be able to handle
something like this...
分かった
（ラビィ）フィー君
Understood.
Fee-kun!
Tanabe, prep some spare
oxygen tanks for me!
（ハチマキ）タナベ
増設ボンベを用意しろ
は… はい！
R-Right!
こいつは いい画(え)が撮れそうだ
This is gonna make for
some awesome footage...
But this is Debris Section's last day.
You don't have to try so hard...
今日で デブリ課は最後なんだ
そんなに頑張らなくたってさ
（タナベ）あっ でも機雷って
人力で壊せるんですか？
But can we destroy
the mine manually?
（ユーリ）
コネクターを持っていってもらおう
I'll have him take a connector along.
We can feed it false data through the Navstar.
ナブスター経由で
機雷に うその情報を伝えればいい
（ラビィ）やめろよ
Don't do it!
（タナベ）独りぼっちで
浮かんでいると思わせるんですか
Oh, we're going to make it think that it's
floating out there all alone, huh?
（ラビィ）やめろって
I said, don't do this!
（フィー）
だましさえすれば近づけるからな
If we can manage to fool it,
we can close in.
Then we hit it with Toy Box's
arm until it stops working.
あとは ToyBox(トイボックス)のアームで
機雷の機能をたたき壊す
Please, don't do this...
やめてくれ
Hachimaki, did you
get all that?
（フィー）ハチマキ 聞こえてた？
Yeah. Find out where the connecter hooks up.
I'm gonna make this work...
（ハチマキ）ああ
コネクターの取り付け位置を
探ってくれ
絶対に成功させて…
やめろーっ！
（ハチマキ）あ？
I SAID STOP!
ラビィ
テクノーラが社会の全てじゃ…
Lavie, there's more to
the world than Technora.
分かってる！ けど…
I know that!
But...
あの… いちばん上のコラナは
頭のいい子でさ
Well... My oldest, Khorana, is a bright girl.
I want to send her to a private school if I can.
できれば私立に行かせてやりたい
Haal loves space, and said that
she wanted a telescope.
ハールは宇宙が好きで
望遠鏡が欲しいって言うんだ
ムシャラフは まだ幼いけど
音楽の才能があって―
Musharraf is
still little,
...but he's got a gift for music, so I want
to get him sitar or piano lessons.
シタールかピアノを
習わせてやりたい
I can't be with them as
their father anymore,
私は もう父親として
そばにいてやれないから―
...so all I can do now
is earn money for them.
お金を稼ぐぐらいしか
できることは…
頼むよ 頼むよ みんな
So please...
Please, everyone!
I can't afford
to be fired!
私は クビになるわけには
いかないんだ
（フィー）
タナベ 増設ボンベを早く届けな
Tanabe, get those spare
oxygen tanks to him ASAP.
（タナベ）ア… アイ コピー
I-I copy!
フィー君！
（フィー）言っただろ
Fee-kun!
Weren't you listening? Technora might
be a company, but it isn't the whole world.
テクノーラは
会社であっても社会じゃない
Besides, even if Debris Section
is going to be disbanded,
そして たとえデブリ課が
解散するとしても―
...right here and now,
we're still debris haulers!
私たちは まだデブリ屋なんだ
（社員）
業務資料は これで最後ですね
These are the last of the official
documents, then?
はい 多分
Yes, I think so...
（管制官）課長 DS-12が
船外活動員を出すようです
Chief!
It looks like the DS-12 is going
to send out an EVA worker!
I told you to stop them,
didn't I?!
（ゲイハート）
やめさせろと言っただろう？
Can't you even train your men
to obey orders?!
部下の教育もできんのか
（課長）すいません
I'm sorry!
（ノーマン）騒ぐな
（ゲイハート）はっ
Calm down.
（ノーマン）
非常停止システムを使えば済む話だ
We just need to use the emergency
shutdown system, and that'll be that.
（課長）えっ 何ですか？
What's that?
君は 全体会議の資料すら
把握していないようだな
I see you don't follow the material
from our general meetings.
対テロリスト用の
セキュリティーとして―
As part of our anti-terrorism
security measures,
我が社の宇宙船には―
...every one of our ships has been fitted with a
device that allows us to shut it down from here.
こちらから停止させる機能を
付け加えてあるだろう
でも 彼らは
デブリを拾おうとしているだけで
But they're only trying to pick up
a piece of debris!
あれはマズいんだよ
We can't let them
do that.
どうして？
（ゲイハート）それは…
Why not?
Well... I don't need to explain
myself to you.
（ノーマン）説明の必要などない
さあ 君の番だ
All right, now it's
your turn.
事業部長と担当課長の承認で
プログラムは発動される
The program will activate once approved by the division director and the head of the relevant section.
ＩＤパスワードぐらい
覚えているだろう
You can at least remember your
own ID password, can't you?
ＩＤパスワードぐらい
覚えているだろう
ううう…
Do you think Senpai's
gonna be okay?
先輩 大丈夫でしょうか？
（ハチマキ）ハァ ハァ ハァ…
An S-class EVA... I have to be
able to do at least this much.
（ハチマキ）ＳクラスのＥＶＡ
これくらいやれないと
Hurry up and input your code,
you scum!
とっととやれ このクズが
あの…
Um...
This will shut down Toy Box, won't it?
止まっちゃうんですよね
ToyBox
I mean, this is
their last job and all...
最後の仕事ですし
それがどうした
What about it?
Um...
その…
ああっ
忘れちゃいました 暗証番号
I forgot it! I forgot my security code.
ふざけるな！
（課長）ひいっ
Stop fooling around!
I'm so sorry, I've always been
the forgetful type!
すいませんね
もともと忘れっぽいたちでして
もうすぐ定年ですし
めっきり記憶が…
Plus, I'm about to retire, and my
memory's getting noticeably worse.
誕生日だったかな？
それとも結婚記念日？
Maybe it was
my birthday...
Or maybe my
wedding anniversary!
（ハチマキ）
ハァ ハァ ハァ ハァ…
相対速度が…
My relative velocity's too...
Almost there!
もう一息 なんとか…
Have to... grab on!
お前は…
やった
I did it?
ああ… 俺は…
I...
やりましたよ 先輩が
Senpai did it!
まっさか ほんとにできるなんてね
I wouldn't believe it if I hadn't
seen it with my own eyes.
Hey, that guy's
pretty good!
おお やるなあ 彼
（ゲイハート）この半課者が！
You Half Section lowlife! Quit your faking,
you're not fooling anybody!
わざとらしい芝居を
打っているんじゃない！
ああっ 本当なんです
It's the truth!
もういい
（ゲイハート）あっ…
Enough.
Navstar connection
status is nominal.
（ユーリ）
ナブスターとの接続状態 良好
Okay, we fooled
the mine!
（フィー）よし！ 機雷をだました
Center of mass
is stable.
重心は安定
I copy. Leave the
rest to me.
（フィー）アイ コピー
あとはこっちに任せて
（警告音）
ナブスターが
アクセスを拒否してる
Navstar's denying access?
（警告音）
（フィー）あっ…
それじゃ
機雷をだませないじゃないか
But that means we won't
be able to fool the mine!
（ノーマン）諦めろ 半課ども
Give it up, you Half Section halfwits.
I've cut your Navstar access from here.
Your little ploy ends here.
ナブスターとの接続は
こちらでカットした
君たちの小細工も ここまでだ
Leave that orbit
right now.
今すぐに その軌道を離れろ
If you don't do it quickly, DS-12's systems might
be fried, and you'll end up dead in space, too.
急がねば―
DS-12も システムをやられて
漂流することになる
ハハッ もっとも
もう間に合わんかもしれんがな
Of course, maybe it's
already too late.
（ハチマキ）くっ…
Hey! What do you mean,
dead in space?
ちょっと 漂流って何ですか
You aren't saying that they're
all going to die, are you?!
もしかして
みんな死んじゃうようなことを
Let go of me!
離したまえ
I'm begging you! Anything but that!
（課長）
お願いします それだけは
I don't need trash like Debris Section
in my division!
デブリ課なんてゴミはな
私の事業部には必要ないんだ！
（課長）あたっ ああっ…
（エーデル）課長補佐
Assistant Chief!
（ノーマン）まったく…
デブリのほうが まだマシだ
I swear, give me debris
any day.
お前らと違って
リサイクルして金になるからな
We can recycle debris and make money
off it, unlike you people.
なあ？
Right?
ううっ うっ ううう…
Junk jockeys being set adrift and becoming
debris themselves is poetic justice!
デブリ屋が漂流して
デブリになるのも 自業自得
Now that I'm division
director, I'll...
私が事業部長になったからには…
（課長）
あんたの事業部に必要なくても―
Even if you don't need us in your division,
the human race needs us!
人類には必要なんだーっ！
あっ 非常電源に
We just went to
emergency power!
What happened? Did the mine get you?!
（ハチマキ）
どうした？ やられたか
Yeah, but our communications and life
support systems seem to be working.
（フィー）ああ
でも 通信と生命維持系はなんとか
I copy! I'll fiddle with the mine's systems
and try to do something on this end.
（ハチマキ）アイ コピー
こちらでなんとか
機雷のシステムをいじってみる
（ノーマン）うおーっ
（課長）うっ ううっ
You bastard!
How dare you lay your hands
on the division director?!
（ゲイハート）
ああっ 事業部長に何を
勤務時間は終了しました
My work hours
just ended.
今の私は テクノーラの
派遣社員ではないと言ったんです
That means that right now, I'm no longer
a temp worker under contract to Technora!
（殴る音）
（ゲイハート）うおっ
（管制官たち）おっ？
Hey, Half Section's going
crazy up there!
（管制官１）
おい 半課が暴れてるぞ
（管制官２）誰か 警備員
Somebody! Call security!
（課長）この人殺し！
You murderer! If they don't pick up debris,
space development will stop in its tracks!
みんながデブリを拾わなきゃ
宇宙開発は 進まないんだぞ！
（ノーマン）何を今更…
（フィー）やるね 課長
Who do you think you are?
Security, clean up this trash!
- That's telling him, Chief.
（ノーマン）何を今更…
（フィー）やるね 課長
（ゲイハート）警備員
このゴミどもを片づけろ
（エーデル）手を出すな！
Keep your hands off me! Come any closer,
and I'll sue you for sexual harassment!
（タナベ）エーデル
これ以上 近づいたら
セクハラで訴えるよ
- Edel...
これ以上 近づいたら
セクハラで訴えるよ
（課長）みんなを返して
Give me back my people!
Fee-san! Yu-chan!
（課長）みんなを返して
フィーさん ユーちゃん ハッちゃん
愛(あい)ちゃん ラビィちゃーん
Ha-chan! Ai-chan! Lavie-chan!
（ゲイハート）
うるさい！ この半課者が
Shut up, you Half Section halfwit!
（ノーマン）
早く こいつらを捕まえろ！
Hurry up and grab
these two!
Right here and now,
Debris Section is hereby disbanded!
デブリ課は 今 この場で解散だ！
じゃあ 誰が宇宙を守るの？
Who's gonna keep
space safe, then?
You keep space safe,
don't you, Dad?
お父さんは
宇宙を守ってるんでしょ？
Everybody says that spaceships can go into
space because you pick up debris, Daddy.
（子供２）
お父さんがデブリを拾ってるから
宇宙船が通れるって
デブリ屋のほうが カッコいいよ！
It's cooler to be
a debris hauler!
ＯＫ ベイビー
Okay, baby...
（フィー）
おい ラビィ どこ行くんだよ
Hey! Lavie, where
are you going?
（ユーリ）ラビィさん
Lavie-san!
（課長）
やめて そこ こそばいの
Please! Stop! I'm ticklish there!
（エーデル）あんた 女を相手に
タイマン 張れねえってのか
What's the matter?
You're holding
back because I'm woman?
くっ さすが軍用 頑丈だな
That's a military bird for you...
This thing's built tough.
Fee-san! Our emergency power's only
gonna last another ten minutes!
フィーさん 非常電源が
あと10分しか もちません
アームは動かせない
I can't get the arm to work. We don't
have any way to smash the mine.
もう機雷のシステムを
破壊する手段が…
分かった ここまでだな
All right, I get it. I guess that's that.
Fee-san...
フィーさん
乗員の安全を守るのも
船長の仕事… おっ
Ensuring the safety of her crew
is part of a captain's...
乗員の安全を守るのも
船長の仕事… おっ
（作動音）
アーム 動かせたんですか？
Did you get
the arm working?!
いや
システムはダウンしたままで…
No, that system
is still down...
What did you people
do this time?!
（パイロット）
あんたら今度は何やった？
（監督）知らねえって
Don't look at me! We've got
our hands full with filming!
こっちは
撮影で手いっぱいなんだからよ
まさか 作業船でラビィが…
Wait, don't tell me Lavie is over
in the work ship, and he...
えっ でも
システムダウンしてるんじゃ…
But aren't their
systems down, too?
そうか 20年以上前の船だから―
Oh, I get it! That ship
is over 20 years old,
...so the arm can be operated manually,
just like on the old Toy Box!
前のToyBoxと同じで―
アームなら
マニュアル操作でも動かせる
Let's see... It's in hydraulic mode right now,
so I need to return it to neutral, and...
（ラビィ）えーっと モードは
ハイドロに切り替えてあるから―
ニュートラルに戻して
（ハチマキ）ラビィ ここだ！
ここをぶったたけ！
Lavie! Over here! Smash it over here!
早くしないと本気でヤバい
Do it soon, or we're
in serious trouble!
聞こえてんのか？ おい！
Do you read me?! Hey!
ああ 分かった
I've got it!
（ノーマン）
いや 分かってないな 宴会屋
No, I don't think you do,
entertainment boy.
（ノーマン）
いや 分かってないな 宴会屋
（ラビィ）うっ
（ノーマン）やめないと
出世どころか会社にも残れないぞ
If you don't stop this, you won't be
moving up, you'll be moving out.
（ノーマン）やめないと
出世どころか会社にも残れないぞ
（ラビィ）あっ
総務の係長にしてやると言ったのを
忘れたのか！
Have you forgotten that I said I'd make
you manager of General Affairs Section?
総務の係長にしてやると言ったのを
忘れたのか！
（フィー･タナベ）え？
お前たちにとっては
会社が全てだろ！
The company is all you people
have, am I right?
If you defy the company
and get thrown out,
会社に逆らって放り出されて
どこに居場所を探すつもりだ！
...who else is going to give you
a place where you can belong?!
そうなんですよね
会社人としては分かるんですよ
Yes, I suppose that's true.
As a company man, I understand that.
でも…
But...
私の居場所
the place I belong...
フッ フフフ… 駄目だなあ 私は
I just can't win, can I?
No matter what I do, I'll...
何をやっても
だから せめて―
So at least I can be...
At least Daddy can be...
お父さんは… お父さんは…
At least your Daddy...
宇宙を守るデブリ屋なんだーっ！
can be a debris
hauler who keeps space safe!
（タナベ）やったー！
He did it!
（監督）うん ナイス
Nice!
DS-12が戻った！？
The DS-12 is
back online?!
うわーい！
（ノーマン）んんっ
Yahoo!
Oh. Um. I finally remembered it. My code, I mean.
あっ や… やっと思い出したんで
暗証番号 アハッ
（ラビィ）
ハハハ… やっちまった
I went and did it
this time...
（ユーリ）
目標デブリの機能停止を確認
System shutdown of target
debris confirmed.
Nicely done, Father.
やりましたね おとうさん
（フィー）ラビィ 見直したよ
I was wrong
about you, Lavie!
ちきしょう 今夜は飲むぞ！
Oh, screw it! I'm gonna
throw some back tonight!
You're all invited! Got it?!
みんなもつきあえ いいな！
（一同）ウィー コピー
We copy!
（一同の笑い声）
（タナベ）おかえりなさい
Welcome back!
ああ
Hey.
Lately, I had been thinking that you
haven't been acting like yourself,
最近の先輩 らしくないなって
思ってたんですけど
...but you're still in there,
all right!
でも やっぱり先輩ですね
いざというときには ちゃんと
When the chips were down,
you came through just fine!
先輩が
あのＥＶＡを成功させたから―
We were able to shut down the mine
because you pulled off your EVA!
機雷を止めることが
できたんですよ
やっぱり すごいです
You're amazing,
all right!
そうか 俺は すごいか
I am? You think I'm amazing?
（タナベ）ええ！
Yep!
タナベ
Tanabe.
はい
Yes?
（ハチマキ）俺 会社 辞めるわ
I'm quitting
the company.
は？
でも デブリ課が
解散っていうだけで まだ…
But they only said that Debris Section
was disbanded. There's still...
No, it's not about that. It's just that...
いや そのことじゃなくて その…
デブリ屋は もう終わりだ
I'm not a hauler anymore.
I'm done with debris.
♪～
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
♪今日も一日が終わって
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
♪気楽にいこうぜ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
♪新しいドア叩いて
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
♪ひとつひとつ
歩いてゆこう
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
♪君も僕もすべての人も
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
♪～
Next Time
Endings are Always...